Kotschnig, Walter Maria; Papers ger053
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Walter Maria Kotschnig Papers
1920-1984
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger053
22.5 cubic ft.
The Walter Maria Kotschnig Papers, 1920-1984, focus on two major aspects of Kotschnig's life, his early career with the International Student Service, 1936-1944, and his diplomatic career with the United States Department of State and the United Nations, 1945-1971, in particular his representation on the United Nations Economic and Social Council.
Biographical Sketch
Walter Maria Kotschnig was born in Judenburg, Austria on April 9, 1901. He attended elementary school (Volksschule) in his hometown of Judenburg and continued his secondary school studies (Realgymnasium) in Graz, Austria, where he headed one of the first student governments organized in Austria. Kotschnig continued his university studies at the University of Graz, moving to the University of Kiel in 1922 where he received his Ph.D. in political science in 1924. In the same year, he married Elined Prys, a psychological consultant from Talgarth, Wales.
In 1925 Kotschnig joined the International Student Service in Geneva, Switzerland, a commitment which lasted nearly twenty years. During the following year, Kotschnig spent three months touring the United States speaking on behalf of the International Student Service. The next year (1927) he became General Secretary of the organization, a position he maintained until 1934, when he became involved with activities of the League of Nations, serving as Director of the High Commission for Refugees from Germany from 1934 to1935.
Because of his outspoken criticisms of Hitler and National Socialism, Kotschnig realized he could not remain in Austria with his family, and in 1936 he immigrated to the United States with his wife and three children. He secured a position as Professor of Comparative Education at Smith and Mt. Holyoke Colleges in Massachusetts, which he held from 1937 to 1944, but still continued to lecture throughout the country on educational topics, with special emphasis on education in Nazi Germany, as well as on the dangers of National Socialism. During this time, Kotschnig also remained active in the International Student Service and its eventual successor, the World Student Service.
In 1944, Kotschnig began his diplomatic career with his appointment to U.S. government service as a specialist on international organization. In this capacity, he attended the Dumbarton Oaks Conferences in Washington, D.C. (1944) and in San Francisco (1945) in preparation for the establishment of the United Nations, as well as preparatory conferences for the formation of the United Nations Economic and Social Council. Over the next three decades, Kotschnig served as Director of the Office of International Economic and Social Affairs (1949-1961), Special Advisor in the Bureau of International Organization Affairs (1962-1965), and as Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for International Organizations (1965-1971). In his capacity of Deputy U.S. Representative on the Economic and Social Council for over twenty-five years, Kotschnig attended 45 out of 49 sessions of the U.N. Economic and Social Council before his retirement in 1971.
In addition to his speaking engagements, Kotschnig also published numerous articles in journals and books. His book publications include: The University in a Changing World (with his wife, 1932); Unemployment in the Learned Professions (1937); and Slaves Need No Leaders (1943). Walter Maria Kotschnig died in Newtown, Pennsylvania on June 23, 1985.
Chronology of Events
April 9, 1901 Born in Judenburg, Austria, son of Ignaz and Therese Huber Kotschnig.
1907-1912 Attended elementary school (Volksschule).
1912-1919 Attended secondary school (Realgymnasium) in Graz, Austria
1918-1919 Headed one of the first student governments established in Austria.
1919 Graduated from the Realgymnasium in Graz.
1920-1924 Studied first at the University of Graz, then (1922) the University of Kiel in Germany.
1924 Graduated from the University of Kiel with a Ph.D. in political science.
Dec. 10, 1924 Married Elined Prys of Talgarth, Wales, a psychological consultant.
1924-1925 Served as a first assistant at the Institute of World Economics in Kiel.
1925 Joined the staff of the International Student Service in Geneva.
1926 Three-month lecture tour in the United States. Awarded St. Sava Order of Yugoslavia.
1927-1934 General Secretary of the International Student Service.
1929 Awarded the Officers Cross, Civil Service Order of Bulgaria.
1932 Edited with his wife, The University in a Changing World; A Symposium.
1934-1935 Worked in London and Geneva on the staff of the League of Nations as Director of the High Commission for Refugees from Germany, dealing with resettlement problems.
1936 Moved to the United States with his wife and three children.
Jan.-Feb. 1936 Series of lectures before the Des Moines Public Education Forums.
1937 Publication of Unemployment in the Learned Professions; an International Study of Occupational and Educational Planning.
1937-1944 Taught at Smith and Mt. Holyoke Colleges in Massachusetts as a Professor of Comparative Education.
1942 Became an American citizen.
1943 Publication of Slaves Need No Leaders.
1944 Entered United States Government service as a specialist on international organization.
1944-1945 Took part in preparations for the establishment of the United Nations at the Dumbarton Oaks Conferences in Washington (1944) and San Francisco (1945); represented the United States at sessions of the International Labor Organization in Paris (1945).
1945-1947 Became acting chief of the Division of International Organizational Affairs of the State Department in 1945, chief in 1947.
1945 Attended the first preparatory conference for the United Nations Economic and Social Conference in London. Received honorary LLD degree from Rockford College, Illinois.
1946-1947 Served as Acting Executive Secretary to the Preparatory Commission of UNESCO in London (1946); attended UNESCO General Conference meetings in Paris (1946) and Mexico City (1947).
1946-1952 Served as a Trustee of the International Institute of Education.
1946 Became Associate executive secretary and consultant of the U.N. Sub-commission of Economic Reconstruction of Devastated Areas, investigating the physfacet of war damages in Czechoslovakia and in Poland.
1949 Represented the United States at sessions of the International Labor Organization in Geneva, as well as two meetings of the Governing Body of the ILO.
1949-1961 Director of the Office of International Economic and Social Affairs.
1950 Attended the U.N. conference on Technical Assistance in New York; was advisor to the United States delegation to the U.N. General Assembly.
1957 Took active part in the creation of the U.N. Technical Assistance Program.
1962-1965 Special Advisor in the Bureau of International Organization and Affairs.
1962 Awarded the personal rank of Minister by President John F. Kennedy.
1965-1971 Served as Deputy Assistant Secretary of State.
July 1971 Shortly before his retirement, received a personal tribute at the 49th session of the Economic and Social Council, after having attended 45 of the 49 sessions of ECOSOC.
1971 Retirement from public service.
June 23, 1985 Died in Newtown, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Contents
The Walter Maria Kotschnig Papers, 1920-1984, focus on two major aspects of Kotschnig's life, his early career with the International Student Service, 1936-1944, and his diplomatic career with the United States Department of State and the United Nations, 1945-1971, in particular his representation on the United Nations Economic and Social Council.
The materials in the collection from Kotschnig's years of service with the International Student Service are extensive and include correspondence, manuscripts, publications and minutes of meetings. In addition, Kotschnig's speeches and lectures, which also date predominantly from the years 1936-1944, deal with educational issues as well as with anti-Hitler and anti-National Socialism topics.
Kotschnig's later diplomatic career, both with the U.S. Department of State and the United Nations Economic and Social Council, 1945-1971, is also represented in the collection. The collection contains primarily de-classified items and personal correspondence during these years, however, a collection of over 1000 photographs in the collection document Kotschnig's diplomatic career. Included are photographs of Kotschnig with other dignitaries and heads of state at sessions of the U.N. Economic and Social Council, as well as meetings of the UN Commission to Study War Devastated Areas, 1944-1946, the Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East (ECAFE) and the Economic Commission for Africa (ECA), 1956-1965.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 10 series.
Acquisition Information
All processed items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Walter M. Kotschnig in March 1981. A small accession of correspondence and professional files of Walter Maria Kotschnig's was donated in December 2024 by Catherine Hale and Nathalie Nelson. Their mother acquired these materials at an estate auction held at the retirement home where Mr. Kotschnig resided following his death. Their mother found the materials in a box of books of Mr. Kotschnig's that she had purchased at the auction.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Public Servants; Political Science; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Exiles' writings, German.; Authors, German--20th century.; Articles; Manuscripts; Correspondence; Kotschnig, Walter M. (Walter Maria), b. 1901; United Nations
- Biographical and Document Files, 1927-1974; 1; 44 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains both biographical and autobiographical materials, as well as documents pertaining to Kotschnig's early involvement with the International Student Service (I. S. S.), as well as his later diplomatic career with the U. S. Department of State and the United Nations. In addition to copies of Kotschnig's unpublished autobiography, entitled "The Quest for Survival", the series also contains a four-part chronology of Kotschnig's life, 1901-1956, prepared by his father, Ignaz Kotschnig. The collection also contains numerous clippings, 1927-1972, which document Kotschnig's activities, including his lectures and reviews of his books.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Kotschnig, Ignaz. "Walter. 1901 bis 21. Maerz 1938". With the note, "Meinem Sohne zum 38. Geburtstage am 9. April 1938", Undated; Typescript (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 1)
  - Kotschnig, Ignaz. "Walter. 15 Mai 1938 bis 30. Juni 1952", Undated; Typescript, cc (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 2)
  - Kotschnig, Ignaz. "Walter. 1. Juli 1952 bis 31. Dezember 1954", Undated; Typescript, cc (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 3)
  - Kotschnig, Ignaz. "Fortsetzung. 1.1.1955 bis 31.12. 1956", Undated; Typescript (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 4)
  - Kotschnig, Ignaz. "Abschriften von Briefen Walters", 1920-1921 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 5)
  - Kotschnig, Walter M. "Quest for Survival: Personal Reflections" with the notation "First Draft", 1978 February (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 6)
  - Kotschnig, Walter M. "Quest for Survival: Personal Reflections" Dated Annex with the notation "First Draft", 1978 May (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 7)
  - Kotschnig, Walter M. "The Quest for Survival: The McCarthy Era", Undated; Manuscript (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 8)
  - Kotschnig, Walter M. "Quest for Survival", Undated; Notes, background materials (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 9)
  - Early publications:Maturazeitung. Realgymnasium in Graz. Edited by Kotschnig. 1920; "Wszechswiatowy Zwiazek Akademików a kwestja zydowska", 1928 May (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 10)
  - Certificates, 1927; 1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 11)
  - High Commission for Refugees (Jewish and Other) Coming From Germany. Correspondence and documents concerning Kotschnig's tenure with the Commission, 1934-1935 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 12)
  - Address book, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 13)
  - Memberships, 1930-1944; 1972 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 14)
  - Selective service documents, 1942 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 15)
  - Fuel rationing documents, 1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 16)
  - Honorary degree, Rockford College, 1944 June 05 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 17)
  - Department of State documents, 1945-1952 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 18)
  - Contract, United Nations, 1946 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 19)
  - "Notes on Contributions", 1940-1952 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 20)
  - "Memorandum made by National Commander George N. Craig of the American Legion regarding the 'Competence' of Walter M. Kotschnig in a speech made on May 16, 1950, before the Silver Anniversary Banquet of the Chicago Accident & Health Assoc. at Hotel La Salle, Chicago, Illinois", 1950 June 19 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 21)
  - "Investigative Interview. In the Matter of: Walter Kotschnig". Dept. of State, Office of Security, 1953 April 13 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 22)
  - "Background Information on Mr. Walter M. Kotschnig", 1953 April 18 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 23)
  - Kotschnig's defense against "derogatory" allegations concerning his activities with the I.S.S., 1953 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 24)
    Includes supporting documents from 1939-1944, correspondence.
  - Invitations to official events, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 25)
  - Inaugural invitation, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 26)
  - Passports, Austrian and U.S., Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 27)
  - Curriculum vitae, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 28)
  - "Annotated Bibliography", Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 29)
  - United Nations contracts, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 30)
  - U.N. Administrative expenses. Records, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 31)
  - Records of payments, honoraria received, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 32)
  - U.N. travel vouchers, receipts, etc., 1970-1973 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 33)
  - Retirement letters, listing, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 34)
  - Golden wedding anniversary, 1974 December 10 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1930s (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 36)
  - Unemployment in the Learned Professions. Reviews, 1937 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1940s (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 38)
  - Slaves Need No Leaders. Reviews, 1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 39)
  - Clippings, 1950s (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1950s (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 41)
  - The United Nations and Economic and Social Cooperation. Reviews, 1957 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 42)
  - Clippings, 1960s (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 43)
  - Clippings, 1970s (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Document ), Folder 44)
- Correspondence, 1927-1984; 2; 1402 folders
  The correspondence files contain circa 10,910 items of correspondence, arranged in four sub-series: correspondence with individuals connected with the International Student Service and related organizations; general correspondence files; correspondence concerning lecture engagements; Kotschnig's correspondence dating from his years of service with the U.S. Department of State and the United Nations.
  - Correspondence with individuals connected with the International Student Service (I.S.S.), the Work Camps for America of the I.S.S., the European Student Relief Fund, the World Student Service and the World Student Service Fund, 1932-1971; 1936-1943; 2.1; 142 folders
    This series of correspondence dates predominately from the years 1936-1943 and contains approximately 2345 items of correspondence, consisting of letters to Kotschnig, carbons of many of his own letters, as well as third party letters which were sent to him. The correspondence documents the history of the International Student Service in the United States, its connection to the European Student Relief Fund, and its subsequent evolution into the World Student Service and the World Student Service Fund. The most substantial correspondent is Alfred E. Cohn (212 items), but the collection also includes correspondence with many of the individuals involved with these organizations: Edward Bradby, Margaret J. Brown, Joseph Cadden, André de Blonay, Clyde Eagleton, Roland A. Elliott, William G. Fletcher, Kenneth Holland, Ruth Hubbard, Alvin S. Johnson, Robert E. Lane, Joseph P. Lash, Charlotte Löhrig, Robert C. Mackie, Louise Morley, William Allan Neilson, Michael Pobers (Pobereszki), Harper W. Poulsen, Eliot D. Pratt, Trude W. Pratt, Wilmina Rowland, Max H. Schneebeli, Robert G. Spivack, Anne Wiggin and Arnold Wolfers.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Baerwald, Paul, 1939; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 1)
    - Bagby, Philip, 1939; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 2)
    - Beatty, Grace Hoover (International Student Committee), 1937-1940; 15 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 3)
    - Bilheimer, Robert S., 1940-1942; 19 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 4)
    - Black, Algernon D., 1941-1943; 1951; 13 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 5)
    - Boggio, Rachel, 1940; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 6)
    - Bogoslovsky, Boris B., 1942-1943; 5 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 7)
    - Bradby, Edward, 1937-1938; 52 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 8)
    - Bradby, Edward, 1939-1940; 23 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 9)
    - Brown, Dale D., 1942; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 10)
    - Brown, Margaret (Margot) J., 1941-1942; 25 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 11)
    - Cadden, Joseph, 1936-1941; 23 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 12)
    - Champney, Mary, 1942; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 13)
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 1936-1940; 50 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 14)
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 1941; 35 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 15)
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 1942; 50 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 16)
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 1943; 60 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 17)
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 1944-1946; 17 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 18)
    - Coleman, A. John, 1942; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 19)
    - Conner, Frances R., 1941-1943; 4 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 20)
    - Coon, Hildur, 1942-1943; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 21)
    - Crandall, Ella Phillips, 1932-1938; 5 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 22)
    - Currier, Raymond, 1940; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 23)
    - Datta, Rena, 1936-1969; 19 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 24)
    - de Blonay, André (Yngve Frykholm), 1939-1950; 61 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 25)
    - de Laban, Juana, 1942-1943; 4 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 26)
    - Deeny, Catherine (Kay) A., 1940; 17 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 27)
    - Dickstein, Leopold, 1943; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 28)
    - Donick, Emily, 1940-1941; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 29)
    - Eagleton, Clyde (Commission to Study the Organization of Peace), 1939-1943; 58 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 30)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1943; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 31)
    - Elliott, A. Roland (National Council of Student Christian Associations; World Student Relief), 1940-1944; 81 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 32)
    - Espy, R. H. Edwin, 1940-1944; 8 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 33)
    - Feldmann, Alexandra (Sandra), 1943-1944; 6 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 34)
    - Fisher, Edgar J. (Institute of International Education), 1938-1943; 18 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 35)
    - Fletcher, William G., 1938-1942; 50 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 36)
    - Foerster, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1934; 1942; 6 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 37)
    - Fox, Evelyn (Mrs. Charles Beresford), 1936-1966; 5 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 38)
    - Frame, Rosamond, 1938; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 39)
    - French, Eleanor, 1941; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 40)
    - Gideonse, Harry D., 1939-1945; 3 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 41)
    - Grant, Maude, 1943; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 42)
    - Griffith, Helen, 1941; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 43)
    - Gross, Alice C., 1939; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 44)
    - Herman, Henry B., 1942-1943; 4 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 45)
    - Hewes, Amy, 1940-1941; 4 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 46)
    - Holland, Kenneth & Mary (American Youth Commission of the American Council on Education; Institute of International Education, 1938-1952; 44 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 47)
    - Hoor, Ernest, 1941; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 48)
    - Hubbard, Ruth (Institute of International Education), 1937-1949; 36 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 49)
    - Hutchins, William J., 1940; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 50)
    - Johnson, Alvin S. (The New School for Social Research), 1940-1943; 22 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 51)
    - Kitchen, William (The Student Christian Movement in New England), 1940-1949; 15 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 52)
    - Korsch, Barbara, 1941; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 53)
    - Kraus, Hertha (Refugee Section of the American Friends Service Committee), 1939-1943; 12 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 54)
    - Kridl, M., 1941; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 55)
    - Kruger, Joseph, 1938-1940; 4 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 56)
    - Ladd, Edward T., 1942-1944; 7 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 57)
    - Lane, Joseph, 1940; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 58)
    - Lane, Robert E. (Intercollegiate Committee to Aid Student Refugees, Work Camps for America of International Student Service), 1940-1941; 24 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 59)
    - Laprade, W. T., 1939; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 60)
    - Lash, Joseph P., 1938-1942; 1970; 79 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 61)
    - Lee, Josephine, 1940-1942; 26 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 62)
    - Lenel, Rosemarie, 1939; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 63)
    - Levy, Adele Rosenwald, 1943; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 64)
    - Li, K.Z. (National Student Relief Committee), 1941; 2 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 65)
    - Limbert, Paul M., 1939; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 66)
    - Littauer, Lucius N., 1940; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 67)
    - Lobenstine, Susan, 1941; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 68)
    - Löhrig, Charlotte (Lo), 1936-1974; 26 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 69)
    - Lovett, A. Sidney, 1941-1943; 7 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 70)
    - Lowe, Rachel, 1941; 1 item (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 71)